## **MAURICE GOODMAN**

Marine Ecology & Biogeography





### SUMMARY -

As a Research Scientist with the UW Punt lab and NOAA Alaska Fisheries Science Center, my work uses a variety of statistical and computational approaches to examine climate impacts on population and predator-prey dynamics in coastal marine systems to inform conservation and fisheries management. Prior to my current role, I earned my PhD at Stanford's Hopkins Marine Station and worked as a data analyst and field technician for community ecology and behavioral ecology labs at Cal Poly, San Luis Obispo. I'm also passionate about teaching, community outreach and engagement, and open science practices.

EDUCATION	
2024	<b>PhD, Biology</b> Committee: Giulio De Leo, Fiorenza Micheli, Elliott Hazen, Stephanie Brodie, Barnabas Daru
2017	<b>BS, Biological Sciences, Cum Laude</b> Concentration in Marine Biology, Minor in Statistics  California Polytechnic State University SLO
PUBLICATIO	ons ————————————————————————————————————
In Review	<b>Goodman, M.C.</b> et al. Market-driven declines in reef shark abundance on remote central-Pacific atolls highlight challenges to shark conservation in an era of globalization. Marine Ecology Progress Series
In Review	<b>Goodman, M.C.</b> et al. Spatial responses to pH, oxygen, and an oceanographic index increase the extent of projected range shifts in the Bering Sea. Fish and Fisheries
In Review	Kumagai, J., <b>Goodman, M.C.</b> , et al. <i>Trophic cascades in marine protected areas promote resilience of kelp forests to marine heatwaves.</i> Global Change Biology
In Press	Gissi, E., <b>Goodman, M.C.</b> , et al. <i>Sex-based species interactions matter in ecological communities.</i> Trends in Ecology and Evolution
In Press	Rempel, H.S. et al. <i>Ecological drivers of parrotfish coral predation vary across spatial scales.</i> Marine Ecology Progress Series
2023	Faiad, S.M., Williams, M.A., <b>Goodman, M.</b> , et al. <i>Temperature affects predation of schistosome-competent snails by a novel invader, the marbled crayfish Procambarus virginalis.</i> PLoS One, 18(9). doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0290615
2022	Andrzejaczek, S., Lucas, T., <b>Goodman, M.</b> , et al. <i>Diving into the vertical dimension of elasmo-branch movement ecology.</i> Science Advances, 8(33). doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abo1754
2022	<b>Goodman, M.C.</b> et al. <i>Shifting fish distributions impact predation intensity in a sub-Arctic ecosystem.</i> Ecography, doi.org/10.1111/ecog.06084
2022	McCalla, L.B. et al. <i>Effectiveness of a Constructed Wetland with Carbon Filtration in Reducing Pesticides Associated with Agricultural Runoff.</i> Archives of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, doi.org/10.1007/s00244-021-00909-0
2021	O'Leary, J.K., <b>Goodman, M.C.</b> , Walter, R.K., Willits, K., Pondella, D.J., & Stephens, J. <i>Effects of Estuary-Wide Seagrass Loss on Fish Populations.</i> Estuaries and Coasts, doi.org/10.1007/s12237-021-00917-2
2020	O'Leary, J.K., <b>Goodman, M.</b> , Tuda, A., Machumu, M., & West, L. <i>Opportunities and challenges in achieving co-management in marine protected areas in East Africa: a comparative case study.</i> Journal of the Indian Ocean Region, 16(3). doi.org/10.1080/19480881.2020.1825201
2019	Hart, L., <b>Goodman, M.C.</b> , Walter, R.K., Rogers-Bennett, L., Shum, P., Garrett, A.D., Watanabe, J.M.

& O'Leary, J.K. Abalone recruitment in low-density and aggregated populations facing climatic stress. Journal of Shellfish Research, 39(2), 359-373. doi.org/10.2983/035.039.0218

**Goodman, M.C.**, Hannah, S.M., & Ruttenberg, B.I. *The relationship between geographic range extent, sea surface temperature, and adult traits in coastal temperate fishes.* Journal of Biogeography, 46(7), 1438-1450. doi.org/10.1111/jbi.13595

#### OTHER RESEARCH WORKS

**Book Chapter** 

O'Leary, J.K., Bockman, E.E., **Goodman, M.**, Grimsditch, G., Madej, M.A., Mohammed, A., & Tyburczy, J. (2024). *Conserving and Managing Estuaries during Climate Change. In Book: Climate Change and Estuaries*. doi.org/10.1201/9781003126096

Manuscript

Lippert, M., **Goodman, M.C.**, Adams, N. (2021). *Comparative effects of Chemical and Physical Sunscreen on Fertilization of Purple Sea Urchins (Strongylocentrotus purpuratus).* Cal Poly Digital Commons, digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/biosp/44

Technical Report O'Leary, J.K., Tuda, A., Machumu, M., Nyunja, J., & **Goodman, M.C.** (2017). *Technical report to the Western Indian Ocean Marine Science Association. Developing a model for strategic adaptive management of MPAs in the Western Indian Ocean.* 34 pp.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### 2022-2024 Independent Contractor

# NOAA AFSC / University of Washington

Built species distribution models for a suite of Eastern Bering Sea groundfish and crab species as part of the Alaska Integrated Climate Modeling (ACLIM) project. Produced species range and spatial overlap projections under multiple earth systems models. Created an R "Shiny" based web app for navigating outputs (mgoodman.shinyapps.io/aclim2\_sdms\_explorer). Partial research outputs are in review at Fish and Fisheries.

### 2022 Independent Contractor

### **Granite Canyon Marine Labs**

Analyzed data from experiments aimed at reducing wetland agricultural runoff. Produced figures and contributed to writing of peer-reviewed manuscript summarizing results.

### 2017-2018

### Data Analyst & Field Technician

### California Sea Grant

Responsible for the analysis, management, and visualization of ecological and social data from Tanzania, Kenya, and Morro Bay, California in the lab of Dr. Jennifer O'Leary. Assisted with writing reports and manuscripts. Full-time.

#### 2016-2018

#### **Research & Dive Technician**

#### Cal Polv SLO

Summer Worked alongside Dr. Ben Ruttenberg to conduct benthic surveys and fish follows on SCUBA to characterize coral community and document parrotfish feeding behavior in St. Croix, USVI. Responsible for entering and managing photo, video, and GPS data, and for gear and boat

maintenance. Seasonal.

#### 2016, 2018 **Aquarist**

## Central Coast Aquarium

Assisted in managing, training and mentoring volunteers and interns in the husbandry department. Maintained all tanks and systems, collected and acclimated new animals, curated exhibits, and regularly monitored water quality. Part-Time.

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

### 2022, 2024 **Instructor**

## **BIO / OCEANS 143: Quantitative Ecology**

Developed and taught 3 weeks of labs and lectures based on material I designed for the previous years' course (see below), focusing on frequentist parameter estimation and species distribution modeling. Assisted students with labs and assignments and graded student submissions.

### 2021 **Co-Instructor**

### **BIOS 207: Software Engineering for Science**

Co-developed materials for teaching software development concepts (code documentation, version control, modular programming, testing and validation) for "Just Enough Software Engineering for Science" short course. Led discussions, assisted students with programming challenges, and evaluated student assignments.

### 2021 **Teaching Assistant**

**BIOHOPK 143H: Quantitative Ecology** 

Designed and taught 3 weeks of labs and lectures on parameter estimation for nonlinear and dynamic models using frequentist and Bayesian principles, as well as species distribution modeling with GAMs (github.com/mcgoodman/quant-eco-2021). Assisted students in learning material taught by other course instructors, held weekly office hours, and assisted students in designing and executing final projects. Awarded Stanford School of Humanities and Science's "Centennial" Teaching Award and Stanford Biology's "Excellence in Teaching" Award.

### 2019 **Teaching Assistant**

**BIO 85: Evolution** 

Co-developed lesson plans, teaching materials, homework assignments and tests. Led a section where students reviewed and reinforced material from lecture, held weekly office hours, and graded student assignments. Awarded Stanford Biology departments "Excellence in Teaching" Award.

## 2017 **Teaching Assistant**

**ZOO 336: Invertebrate Zoology** 

Prepared lab specimens and activities for class, collected new specimens, demonstrated lab methods and dissections to students, and assisted students with lab and field activities.

#### **OUTREACH, LEADERSHIP, & SERVICE**

#### 2022 - 2023 **President**

### **Hopkins Marine Station Graduate Student Association**

Engaged the graduate student community in multiple community-building initiatives, including organizing inclusivity trainings, social events, and graduate student retreats, representing grad students to Dean and Hopkins faculty and administrative and DEI meetings, and obtaining funds to renovate grad student work & social spaces. Previously served as webmaster for graduate student association (Fall 2019 - Summer 2021).

### 2020-2022 Student Liaison

MARINE

Served for two academic years as Hopkins Marine Station's liaison for Monterey Area Research Institutions' Network for Education (MARINE), an organization of marine science students and early career researchers from seven academic institutions in the Monterey Bay area. Planned networking, social, and community service events.

## 2016-2017 Founder & Vice President

Cal Poly Marine Science Club

Founded and co-lead the Cal Poly Marine Science Club. Organized, planned, and lead events and meetings; managed social media and outreach.

#### 2014-2018

### **Husbandry & Outreach Volunteer**

**Central Coast Aquarium (Non-Profit)** 

Assisted with husbandry tasks such as maintenance of tanks, acclimation of fishes, treatment of diseased fishes, curation of exhibits, preparation of diets, and training of new volunteers. Frequently gave talks and tours to the public, taught grade school programs, and participated in outreach and fund raising. **Over 800 hours volunteered.** 

## FELLOWSHIPS, HONORS, & AWARDS

Salary support Stanford Data Science	Graduate Scholar 50% Tuition & S	2022-2024
Friends of Hopkins Marine Station	Research Grant \$6,500	2022
Myers Oceanographic & Marine Biology Trust	Research Grant \$1,800	2022
Stanford Department of Biology	Excellence in Teaching Award	2021
Stanford School of Humanities & Sciences	Centennial Teaching Award	2021
Tuition & Salary Support National Science Foundation	Graduate Research Fellowship	2019-2023
Cal Poly College of Science & Mathematics	President's List	2014-2016
William & Linda Frost Foundation, Cal Poly SLO	Summer Research Scholarship \$	2016

**Various Projects** 

#### **INVITED PRESENTATIONS**

2024 Incorporating local responses to regional change into Bering Sea range projections. Lowell Wakefield Fisheries Symposium. Talk

#### **CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS**

2024	Ecological impacts of climate-driven species range shifts: inference from multiple methods in		
	the Bering Sea. Stanford Sustainability Data Science. Talk		
2024	Climata Impacts on Drodatar Droy Interactions, implications for Daring Coa fisheries, Ctanford		

Climate Impacts on Predator-Prey Interactions: implications for Bering Sea fisheries. Stanford Resilient Pacific. Talk

Forecasting predator-prey overlap for climate-ready fisheries management in the Bering Sea. World Fisheries Congress. Talk

Forecasting predator-prey overlap for climate-ready fisheries management in the Bering Sea. Western Society of Naturalists. Talk

2023 Shifting fish distributions impact predator-prey interactions in the Eastern Bering sea. Alaska Marine Science Symposium. Talk

2023 Global shark fin demand, small-scale fisheries, and reef sharks: A case study in the Northern Line Islands. Stanford Data Science Conference. Talk

2022 Shifting fish distributions impact predation intensity in a sub-Arctic ecosystem. Ocean Sciences Meeting. Talk

International market demand drives a small-scale Central Pacific reef shark fishery towards collapse. Western Society of Naturalists. Talk

Ecological consequences of climate induced changes in spatial overlap between Eastern Bering Sea walleye pollock and their predators. Western Society of Naturalists. Talk

The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Western Society of Naturalists. Talk

The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate

The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Cal Poly Annual Student Research Symposium. Talk

Long-Term Monitoring of Sea Urchin Settlement Along the California Coast. Cal Poly Annual Student Research Symposium. **Poster** 

The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Central Coast Wildlife Society Annual Wildlife Symposium. Talk

The Relationship Between Geographic Range Extent and Adult Traits in Coastal Temperate Fishes. Western Society of Naturalists. **Poster** 

### FIELD RESEARCH

2017

2017

2016

2023 NOAA Alaska Fisheries Science Center Bering Sea Bottom Trawl Survey

Volunteered on a three week survey leg sorting, sexing, and lengthing specimens as part of the annual Eastern Bering Sea bottom trawl survey which collects data needed for stock assessments and other management models. Lead stomach collection for food habits analysis.

## 2019-2023 Stanford Hopkins Marine Station

**Palumbi lab:** Assisted on field projects in Palau (collecting corals and running heat stress experiments, transplanting corals for common garden experiments) and the California central coast (collecting samples via boat on SCUBA, processing samples). **Other:** Various dives to conduct kelp forest ecological surveys and deploy instrumentation for graduate student projects.

### 2014-2018 Cal Poly San Luis Obispo

### **Ruttenberg & O'Leary Labs**

**Ruttenberg lab:** Collection of coral reef ecological survey data via SCUBA (see Work Experience section), and surveys of Pismo Clam populations on California coastal beaches from Port San Luis to San Diego. **O'Leary lab:** Monthly collection of cobbles via SCUBA for monitoring recruitment of abalone, surveys of eelgrass and associated fish communities via beach seines and monitoring of permanent plots.

### **SCUBA Experience & Certifications**

AAUS Scientific Diver, 60 ft

PADI Divemaster Now Inactive

DAN Diving First Aid for Professional Divers

2015 - Present
2017 - Present
2015 - Present

400+ Total Dives 200+ Scientific Dives

#### **MENTORSHIP**

### 2019, 2022 **REEFS Undergraduate Internship**

### **Stanford University**

**2022:** Mentored two undergraduate students in building out a control system for conducting multiple stressor experiments in aquaria, developing protocols as part of a pilot study, and analyzing data. Students prepared and presented poster to researchers and other students at Hopkins. **2019:** Mentored an undergraduate student in applying machine learning and statistical approaches to model harmful algal bloom incidence in California.

### 2016-2018 Undergraduate research mentor

Cal Poly SLO

Established and led a biweekly sea urchin recruitment monitoring program at Port San Luis as part of the larger Santa Barbara Coastal LTER project. Trained several undergraduates in deploying collection media and sorting and identifying specimens.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

#### Scientific Computing -

R, R Markdown, & RStudio, Stan, GIS (QGIS, R sf & stars packages), git & github

### Statistical Methodology

Bayesian and frequentist linear, nonlinear, and dynamical models; hierarchical, time-series, and spatial models; R statistics packages (rstan, brms, mgcv, glmmTMB, nlme, lme4, VAST, etc.)

### Software Development -

#### R Shiny web apps

ACLIM2 SDMs explorer: mgoodman.shinyapps.io/aclim2\_sdms\_explorer Probability distributions lab: mgoodman.shinyapps.io/distributions-lab

## Reproducible Scientific Code Repositories

Faiad et al. 2023: github.com/wood-lab/Faiad\_et\_al\_2023\_PLoS\_One Goodman et al. 2022: github.com/mcgoodman/Goodman-et-al\_2022\_Ecography Andrzejaczek et al. 2022: github.com/mcgoodman/shark-vertical-overlap O'Leary et al. 2020: github.com/mcgoodman/OLeary-et-al\_2020\_ESCO

#### R Packages

geomViolinDiscrete: github.com/mcgoodman/geomViolinDiscrete

### **SCHOLARLY REVIEWS**

2024	Progress in Oceanoo	aranhy NOAA	Internal Daview (2)
2024	Progress in Oceanoc	arabniv, indaa i	Internal Review (2)

2023 Fisheries Research, Marine Ecology Progress Series, PLoS One

2022 Progress in Oceanography, Animal Biotelemetry, NOAA Internal Review

2021 ICES Journal of Marine Science